<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Queenes vvelles That is, a treatise of the nature and vertues of Tunbridge water. Together, with an enumeration of the chiefest diseases, which it is good for, and against which it may be vsed, and the manner and order of taking it. By Lodvvick Rovvzee, Dr. of Physicke, practising at Ashford in Kent.</title>
            <author>Rowzee, Lodwick, b. 1586.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21426</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116278</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851495</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851495</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16769</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11156)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16769)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 974:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Queenes vvelles That is, a treatise of the nature and vertues of Tunbridge water. Together, with an enumeration of the chiefest diseases, which it is good for, and against which it may be vsed, and the manner and order of taking it. By Lodvvick Rovvzee, Dr. of Physicke, practising at Ashford in Kent.</title>
                  <author>Rowzee, Lodwick, b. 1586.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Iohn Dawson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The Queenes wells.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mineral waters --  England --  Tunbridge Wells --  Therapeutic use --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16769:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16769:1"/>
            <p>THE QVEENES VVELLES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THAT IS,</hi> A Treatiſe of the nature and vertues of <hi>Tunbridge</hi> Water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>TOGETHER,</hi> With an enumeration of the chiefeſt diſeaſes, which it is good for, and againſt which it may be vſed, and the manner and order of taking it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> LODVVICK ROVVZEE, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of Phyſicke, practiſing at <hi>Aſhford</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Imprinted by <hi>Iohn Dawſon.</hi> 1632.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:16769:2"/>
            <p>Recenſui hunc librum, cui titulus eſt, <hi>[The Queenes Welles, or a Treatiſe of the nature and vertues of</hi> Tunbridge <hi>Water]</hi> Qui quidem liber continet triginta et tria folia, in quibus nihil reperio, quod non cùm utilitate publicâ imprimatur, modò intra tres menſes proximè ſequentes typis mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Ex aedibus Fulha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mienſibus, <date>
                     <hi>Iun. 3. 1632.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Guilielmus Bray Epiſcopo Londinenſi Capellanus Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:16769:2"/>
            <p>AS diverſe medicinable waters are daily found out in many places, ſo is it a very profitable labour to make true obſervation of their effects, and beſt manner of vſing them, ſpecially by men of learning and judicious vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and ſuch as haue beene accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to the frequent vſe of them, both in themſelues and others, whereby they may make their obſervations more true and certaine. Such an one wee take this Author to be, concerning the Waters neere <hi>Tunbridge,</hi> whole paines taken herein wee doubt not, but will be very vſefull to all ſuch as ſhall haue occaſion to make tryall of them.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Argent.</hi> Preſident of the Colledge of Phyſitians at <hi>London.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ottuell Meverell.</hi> Fellowes of the ſaid Colledge.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Spicer.</hi> Fellowes of the ſaid Colledge.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16769:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16769:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, EDVVARD Lord Viſcount <hi>Conway</hi> and <hi>Kilulta,</hi> and one of his MAIESTIES moſt Honourable privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of his Kingdome of IRELAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ngratitude is the fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt vice in the world, and as the old ſaying is, <hi>Ingratum ſi dixeris, omnia dixeris.</hi> I may haue incurred the
<pb facs="tcp:16769:4"/>
imputation of it theſe ſix &amp; twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares (for ſo long it is ſince I harboured vnder your Noble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Fathers roofe) for not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing my thankfulneſſe for the courteous vſage I found at his hands, both here in <hi>England,</hi> and at the <hi>Briele</hi> in <hi>Holland.</hi> What want of opportunitie hindered me to expreſſe to him now dead, oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie now offering it ſelfe, I will ſtriue to doe it vnto your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip his living Image. But a ſmall expreſſion it is, God knoweth, yet all I may at this time, and though it be very meane, yet doe I thinke that your Lo<hi rend="sup">p</hi>: will receiue theſe two fountaines of water as courteouſly at my hands, as <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes</hi> did the two handfulls of
<pb facs="tcp:16769:4"/>
Perſian water, which <hi>Sinaetas</hi> offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him. It is the nature of Noble and Generous Spirits not to haue ſo much regard to the worth of the things offered them, as to the affection wherewith they are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. I haue knowne your Lo<hi rend="sup">p</hi>: <hi>a teneris vnguiculis,</hi> and alwayes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, even in your tendereſt yeares, a moſt Noble diſpoſition, and withall both at the <hi>Briele</hi> and at <hi>Leyden</hi> a naturall inclination to follow <hi>Minerva</hi> as well as <hi>Mars.</hi> This, together with the courteous affabilitie it ever pleaſed you to vſe me withall, maketh me now beleeue, that your Lordſhip will giue favourable acceptance to this ſmall labour of mine, for
<pb facs="tcp:16769:5"/>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Acceptiſsima ſemper</l>
                  <l>Munera ſunt, Author quae precioſa facit.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Receiue it then, My Lord, as an earneſt of what would be done, if abilitie concurred with deſire, by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble ſervant, <hi>L. ROVVZEE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16769:5"/>
            <head>A TREATISE CONCERNING THE Nature and vertues of <hi>Tunbridge</hi> Water in KENT.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER I.</hi> Of Water in generall.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit my maine ſcope in this following diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, be concerning <hi>Tunbridg</hi> water, yet will it not be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fruitleſſe, or vnpleaſant, I hope, to the Reader, if I ſay ſomething, as it were by way of Preface, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing water in generall. Water is a ſubſtance ſo abſolutely neceſſary, that no living creature can ſubſiſt without the benefit of it, nor no
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16769:6"/>
tree bring forth its leaues and fruit, nor any plant its ſeede, if they be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of that vivificall moiſture, which maketh them all to grow and proſper. That this is true, you may obſerue it in Summer, for if Raine be wanting but a few weekes, how hinderly be all things? How doe all plants wither in that ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when they ſhould chiefly flouriſh? For this cauſe perhaps it was, that <hi>Heſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odus</hi> thought water to be the moſt ancient of all the elements. Of this opinion alſo was <hi>Thales Mileſius</hi> one of the ſeaven wiſe Grecians, who made water the ſole principle of all things. <hi>Empedocles</hi> likewiſe jumping with them, ſayd that all things were made of water; and <hi>Hippon</hi> in<note n="a" place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> c <hi>2.</hi> de anima.</note> 
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> termes the ſoule water. <hi>Hippocrates</hi> goeth not ſo farre, but yet he calleth water and fire the two principles of life. True it is, that by water <hi>Hippon</hi> doth vnderſtand our ſeede, and <hi>Hippocrates</hi> our ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16769:6"/>
moiſture. The Latins vpon the Etymologie of the word <hi>Aqua,</hi> water, doe derive it from <hi>à et qua, quaſi à qua vivimus, vel à qua omnia fiunt,</hi> by which we liue, or out of which all things are made. Others will haue it <hi>quaſi aequa,</hi> becauſe there is nothing more equall and ſmooth then water, when it is not toſſed with the winde. But<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exercit.</hi> 745.</note> 
                  <hi>Iulius Caeſar Scaliger</hi> diſliketh theſe Etymolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, and will deriue <hi>aqua</hi> from the obſolete Greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which anciently did ſignifie water. This E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement ſeemeth to challenge a kinde of rule and dominion over the reſt, for it eaſily tranſmuteth ayre into it ſelfe, extinguiſheth fire, and devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth earth. And to goe no higher, then our grand-fathers memory, nor farther then our neighbours, the Ocean Sea ſwallowed vp aboue one hundred thouſand Acres of ground at one clap in <hi>Holland.</hi> Nay it aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth even vnto the heavens, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16769:7"/>
which is ſtrange, it doth not onely get vp thither in it ſelfe alone, but carrieth with it whole ſholes of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, heapes of ſtones, and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heavy ſubſtances, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards fall down with it. Moſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures liue without fire, without wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter none; &amp; with water onely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other ſuſtenance, a<note n="c" place="margin">Cael. Rhod. Lib. <hi>13.</hi> c. <hi>23</hi>
                  </note> Spaniſh mayden is reported to haue lived a long time; and <hi>Albertus</hi> writeth of a Melancholy man, who by the ſpace of ſeven weekes lived with water onely, one draught of which he tooke but every other day. The <note n="d" place="margin">d.</note> Lord <hi>Verulam</hi> alſo hath produced his opinion of late, and holdeth that Trees and Plants liue and are nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed meerely by water, and that the earth is as it were, but a <hi>Stabilimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> vnto them, to keepe them ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and from being beaten downe by the winde. Hee proveth it by Roſe buſhes, which being put into water, without any earth, &amp; kept vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16769:7"/>
in the ſame, not onely brought forth leaues, but faire Roſes alſo, And the<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> royall Prophet ſayth, that <hi>a tree planted by the rivers of water, bringeth forth his fruit in due ſeaſon.</hi> Much more might be ſayd concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning water, but becauſe I intend to be briefe, let this ſuffice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER II.</hi> Of the differences of water.</head>
               <p>IN the Creation God ſayd,<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 1.4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>let there be a firmament in the middeſt of the waters, and let it divide the waters from the waters. And GOD made the firmament, and divided the waters, which were vnder the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from the waters, which were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the firmame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 29.10.</note> And <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>that the Lord ſitteth vpon the flood,</hi> that is vpon the Orbe of the waters; and where he exciteth the creatures
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16769:8"/>
to laude the Lord, he ſpeaketh thus, <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 148. v. 4</note> 
                  <hi>Praiſe him ye heavens of heavens, and the waters that be aboue the heavens.</hi> Thoſe waters are likened in another place to a<note n="i" place="margin">Ezech. 1.24.</note> 
                  <hi>terrible chryſtall,</hi> and ſayd to be, as it were,<note n="k" place="margin">Exod. 24.10.</note> 
                  <hi>a paved worke of Saphir ſtone.</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Rabbi Levi Ben Iarehij <hi>in</hi> Gen. c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> And ſome go ſo farre, as to define the place and ſeate of thoſe waters, and ſay, that they are as much aboue the <hi>primum mobile,</hi> as the <hi>primum mobile</hi> is aboue the elementary waters, but whether they ever were there to take the iuſt diſtance, I doe not know. That there ſhould be water aboue the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, many men thinke it ſtrange, and yet the deluge, beſides the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe word of God, proved it to be true. For if all the water of all the Seas, Lakes, Ponds, Rivers, &amp; Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines in the world, had been drawn vp into the heavens, in like manner, as we doe in diſtillations, yet would not their quantitie haue increaſed, but there would haue returned back
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16769:8"/>
againe, by raine, no more, then was aſcended vp, nor ſo much neither perhaps, becauſe though you be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo carefull in your diſtillations, and vſe Glaſſe veſſels neuer ſo well luted, yet will you ſtill receiue ſome loſſe; and ſo the flood had not gone fifteene cubits aboue the higheſt mountaines. But why this ſhould be ſtranger, then all the reſt of the wonderfull works of God, there is no reaſon. The maſſie and heavy Globe of the earth and water ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, as it were, in <hi>aequilibrio</hi> in the center of the world, ſuſpended by the omnipotencie of God. Nay all his workes are vniverſally ſo admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that there is no leſſe wonder in the ſmaleſt Gnat, then in the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt Elephant, in the leaſt weede, that creepeth vpon the ground, then in the talleſt Cedar. But of thoſe waters, which are aboue the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of thoſe, which were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together vnder the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16769:9"/>
namely the Seas, wee ſpeake here but by the way, though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Seas divers curious and pleaſant queſtions might bee hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as touching the ſaltneſſe of it, the ebbing and flowing of the ſame, why it can endure no impure things, and the like. Theſe things I ſay, might bring ſome delight to the Reader, but they are beyond our ſcope, and therefore I will onely ſpeake briefly of thoſe waters, which are <hi>potable,</hi> and in common vſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, either for dyet or Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke.</p>
               <p>They are commonly divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Fountaine-water, River-water, Well-water, raine-water and pond-water. The preheminence thereof is commonly given to Spring-water, but in generall that water is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted beſt and wholeſomeſt for dyet, which is pure, and without any taſt, but ſuch as water ſhould haue. For moſt water retaineth ſome ſavour of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16769:9"/>
the ground through which it run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and albeit to thoſe, who doe not vſe to drinke water, it be imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible, yet divers of thoſe, who drink nothing but water, will as eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceiue a difference betwixt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and water, as wee doe betwixt beere and beere, or wine and wine. The beſt water alſo is lighteſt, but that lightneſſe is not to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by waight (for ſnow-water is moſt light, and yet vnwholeſome) but by the thinneſſe of the parts thereof, and by the ſpeedy heating and cooling of the ſame, as <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> well obſerveth. Let this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to haue beene briefly touched concerning the differences of waters in generall, and let vs now ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with like brevitie concerning the originall of Springs and Rivers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:16769:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER III.</hi> Of the originall of Springs and Rivers.</head>
               <p>IT is a common received opinion, derived from <hi>Aristotle,</hi> that the generation of water proceedeth from ayre condenſated into the ſame, in the bowels of the earth, and diſtilling, as water doth with vs from a Limbicke. But it is hard to imagine how the nature of ayre ſhould bee ſo ſpeedily corrupted, and turned into water, and in that quantitie too, that ſhould maintaine the continuall courſe of ſo many Springs, and ſo great a number of Rivers as are in the world, divers of which are of ſuch vaſtneſſe, and of ſo ſwift a courſe, that a man might juſtly thinke, that the whole element of ayre, which in its owne nature is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16769:10"/>
but very thinne, ſhould ſcarcely ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to maintaine the courſe of that aboundance of water one only day. And as for the reaſon they alledge, that ayre is retained within the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavities</hi> and <hi>poroſities</hi> of the earth, <hi>ad vitandum vacuum,</hi> which nature doth abhorre, and afterwards is converted into water, it is but a very weake one; For thoſe <hi>concavities</hi> are ſtill full of ayre, as well elſe-where, as where Springs and Rivers doe flow. But if the tranſmutation of ayre into water, were the only cauſe of the flowing of all Springs and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, ſurely their ſtreams muſt needs be but narrow, &amp; their courſe ſlow, and of ſmall continuance. Beſides, if this were true, how could the Sea, thinke you, containe that exceſſiue aboundance of water, which perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually runneth into the ſame? The ancient opinion then is the truer, that all fountaines and rivers come from the Sea, and are <hi>tranſcolated</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:16769:11"/>
through the veines and <hi>poroſities</hi> of the earth, where in their paſſage they leaue their ſaltneſſe. <hi>Plato Ariſtotles</hi> Maſter was of this opinion, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him <hi>Thales Mileſius;</hi> as alſo <note n="m" place="margin">In Libro de mundi opificio.</note> 
                  <hi>Philo,</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> Nat. quaeſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Seneca,</hi> and<note n="o" place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> de ortu ſubter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran.</note> 
                  <hi>Georgius Agricola,</hi> which without queſtion they had learned from the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes.</hi> For thus ſpeaketh the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,<note n="p" place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>All the Rivers runne into the Sea, yet the Sea is not full, vnto the place from whence the Rivers come, thither they returne againe.</hi> This is a moſt cleare and expreſſe text, and which alone ſhall ſuffice to proue this point, eſpecially ſeeing the rule and law of Nature doth <hi>ſuffragate</hi> vnto the ſame; For whereſoever there is a repletion, there muſt needs an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuation bee. But ſome perhaps may ſay, wee ſee indeed all Rivers runne into the Sea, but we doe not ſee how they come from it. True, but when wee ſee that for all the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of water, which runneth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16769:11"/>
continually into the Seas, the ſame are not increaſed thereby, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſtill the ſame, we muſt needs imagine that they disburthen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſome where. For otherwiſe, the waters had long agoe over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed the world, and reached vp even vnto heaven, ſeeing that the<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 7.</note> Flood, cauſed bin by raine of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes, aſcended fifteene cubits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the higheſt mountaines. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides our very ſenſes may perſwade vs, that the originall of Springs and Rivers is from the Sea; for divers Springs of freſh water are in ſundry places, which ſeeme to <hi>ſympathize</hi> with the Sea, and to imitate the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof by a kind of ebullition. And which is ſtrange, and yet a thing avouched by divers good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, thoſe things which were caſt into the River of <hi>Alpheus</hi> in <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> were afterwards found in the fountaine called <hi>Arethuſa,</hi> neere <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racuſa</hi> in <hi>Sicilie,</hi> though there bee a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16769:12"/>
great diſtance of Sea and land be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, which gaue occaſion to the ancient Poets (who did vſe to <hi>involue</hi> all the ſecrets of nature in their fables) to faine that <hi>Alpheus</hi> and <hi>Arethuſa</hi> were a couple of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, which were transformed, the one into a River, and the other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a fountaine, and of them ſpeaketh<note n="r" place="margin">Lib. <hi>5.</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam.</note> 
                  <hi>Ovid,</hi> ſaying</p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>In latices mutor, ſed enim cognoſcit amatas,</l>
                  <l>Amnis aquas, poſitó<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> viri, quod ſumpſerat, ore,</l>
                  <l>Vertitur in proprias, quo ſe mihi miſceat, vndas.</l>
               </q>
               <p>But whereas I ſaid before, that for all the water, which runneth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Seas, they remaine ſtill the ſame, I would not be miſtaken, for I know that the Seas haue ſomtimes gone beyond their ordinary bounds and limits, but it hath beene when
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16769:12"/>
they were, as it were commanded ſo to doe by their Creator for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of mens wickedneſſe, or whenſoever men haue gone about to alter the naturall ſeate and ſtate of the ſame, and the ordinary courſe of Rivers.</p>
               <p>Of Gods judgements there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe examples, as<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib</hi> 2. Of <hi>Polybius</hi> that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Greeke Authour, whoſe works I lately fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate into Engliſh, my tranſlation being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die for the Preſſe, if it can finde any roome there. And as for <hi>Polybius,</hi> I dare boldly ſay here by the way, that there is not any better or more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Author extant in his kinde, eſpecially for three ſorts of men, Princes, Stateſmen, and Souldiers. And whereas the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fift was wont to ſay, that there were but three Bookes neceſſary for a Prince, <hi>Polybius</hi> for Warres, <hi>Machiavell</hi> for State-matters and policie, and <hi>Caſtiglio</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, if he aymed at a <hi>compendium</hi> he might very well haue left out the ſecond, ſeeing for State-matters and honeſt policy, enough of it may be found in <hi>Polybius,</hi> who for judgement, ſufficiencie, vertue, and honeſtie (though but an Heathen) went farre beyond <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>vell;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t &amp; ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>ce, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing beene in great pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ie, both in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vill and marſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>res, and fam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rly acqua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nted wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h that great Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>frica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi> &amp; with <hi>Caius Laelius.</hi> Whereas <hi>Machiavell</hi> was but a pettie Secretarie or Towne-Clarke o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Citie of <hi>Florence,</hi> growne famous onely through the wicked Maximes and Poſitions contained in his writings, and eſpecially in his <hi>Prince,</hi> where he ſetteth forth that Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f Men, <hi>Caeſar Borgia,</hi> baſtard-ſonne to the like father, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the ſixt Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> as a patterne to be imitated by ſuch, as deſir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to get rule and dominion to themſelues. And it ſeemeth by a paſſage of the ſeventh Chapter of his <hi>Prince,</hi> that he was acquainted with him, and perhaps a Counſellor of his in his murders, po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ngs, and other deviliſh exploits. But <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lybi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> farre from doing the like, that there are infinite di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in his workes, in which he reprehendeth the vicious act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ons of men more ſharply, then ſome other Authors, which profe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> themſelues Chriſtians.</note> 
                  <hi>Olenus</hi> &amp; <hi>Helice,</hi> two of the 12. Cities which made the Common-wealth of the <hi>Achae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> which a little before the battell of <hi>Leuctra</hi> were drowned by the ſea. <hi>Antiſſa, Tindaric, Burrha</hi> had the like fortune alſo, being ſwallowed vp by the Sea, together with all their Inhabitants. And that it might the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16769:13"/>
better appeare that the finger of God was in it, all ſuch, as thought to haue eſcaped by ſhipping, peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed as well as the reſt, being drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; overwhelmed by the waues. And of thoſe who haue endevoured to contract and pin vp the Sea into narrower limits, by wrlls, dikes, and other workes, diverſe of them haue often ſuſtained great dammage by the ſame; as for example, the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> who, as we ſaid before, loſt aboue 100000. acres of ground by ſuch meanes, which the Sea, after the overthrow of all their dikes and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16769:13"/>
ſtrong workes, tooke away from them, as it were by Letters of repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalls. This were enough to teach men that it is but in vaine to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the order eſtabliſhed by God, and the ordinary courſe of Nature; yet it is worth the noting alſo, and a thing not to be conſidered without admiration, that all thoſe Princes, who purpoſed to cut the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> of <hi>Peloponeſus,</hi> which is a necke of land betwixt two Seas, containing accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Mercator</hi> in his <hi>Atlas Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor,</hi> ſome fiue miles in breadth, dyed all before the worke was begun, as <hi>Caligula, C. Caeſar, Demetrius, Nero,</hi> and <hi>Domitianus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER IIII.</hi> Of waters of ſtrange nature and effects.</head>
               <p>ALL Springs of Waters are actually, either hot or cold. Of thoſe hot Springs ſome
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16769:14"/>
are of ſo exceſſiue heate, that a man would thinke it were water boyling vpon the fire; and amongſt other there is a veine of it running vnder a ſtreete in a village called <hi>Porcet</hi> neere the City of <hi>Akin</hi> in <hi>Germanie.</hi> In the middle of this ſtreete there is a hole, which they call <hi>Hell,</hi> with three or foure barres of yro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> over it, in which the neighbours round about, in the Sommer time, when they haue no fire, doe vſe to ſeeth their egges, letting them downe with a Net into the water, and in a ſmall ſpace of time they may be boyled hard; of which I was twice an eye-witneſſe, being there firſt in the yeare 1610. after the ſiege of <hi>Gulick,</hi> and the yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Towne to the States, with that braue Souldier, Sir <hi>Horace Vere,</hi> now Lord of <hi>Tilbury,</hi> &amp; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time with that worthy Knight, Sir <hi>Henry Palmer,</hi> now Controller of the Navie. The cauſe of thoſe hot Waters is commonly aſcribed to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16769:14"/>
Mines of <hi>Sulphur</hi> or brimſtone in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed within the bowells of the earth. But few of thoſe hot waters, as at <hi>Akin, Porcet,</hi> in the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Mountaines, at <hi>Bathe</hi> in <hi>Sommerſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> and elſewhere, haue any great or extraordinary taſte of brimſtone, as they ſhould of neceſſitie haue, if brimſtone melted and burning were the cauſe of their heate, that minerall being of ſo piercing a nature, and of ſo entenſiue a facultie, that never ſo little of it burning vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a few coales, when our women dry their tiffanies, filleth a whole room with the ſtrong ſent of it. Beſides, ſuch a great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of water running continually, and ſo many yeares and ages toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, had long ſince extinguiſhed thoſe fires; or if there were ſuch flames within the bowells of the earth, the ſame would long agoe dryed vp the water, and reduced the earth into aſhes. Another reaſon there is, that you ſhall finde no hot
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16769:15"/>
Springs where fires doe breake our, and albeit the hill <hi>Veſuvius</hi> &amp; Mount <hi>Aetna</hi> burne continually, yet are there no hot Springs about them, though they be environed by the Sea. And for all the late wonderfull and extraordinary eruption of fire out of the ſaid hill <hi>Veſuvius,</hi> or <hi>Monte de Soma,</hi> as they call it now; which hath beene ſo violent, that the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>Naples,</hi> which are eight or as others ſay twelue miles from the ſame, were all covered very thicke with the aſhes thereof, yet doe they not write that the water which gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed out at the foote of the ſaid hill was hot.</p>
               <p>Beſides, albeit there be many hot waters in <hi>Italie</hi> (for thoſe that haue written of them, reckon few leſſe than threeſcore) yet ſhall you ſee no where a mixture of fire and water in thoſe parts. Which makes me thinke with ſome, that the cauſe of the heate of thoſe waters proceedeth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16769:15"/>
from their motion and agitation in the bowels of the earth, falling from <hi>Cataracts</hi> and broken <hi>Concavities</hi> in the ſame.</p>
               <p>That this may be true, it may be proved by the Sea, for though it be actually cold, yet if it be toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a Tempeſt but of three or foure dayes (and it is ſeldome that a ſtorme laſteth longer) the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thereof will ſometimes become very hot. Beſides, we haue many very <hi>ſulphurous</hi> Springs, which are never but cold; as for example, one of the foure Springs vſed at the <hi>Spa</hi> called <hi>Geronſter,</hi> which taſteth ſo ſtrong of the brimſtone (as my ſelfe can ſpeake by experience) that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of thoſe, who drinke of it, are conſtrained to hold their noſes whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt they are a drinking, and the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurous</hi> fumes of it are ſo piercing, that they doe ſpeedily intoxicate the braine, and cauſe drunkenneſſe, though it be but for a little time,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16769:16"/>
being ſoone diſcuſſed away.<note n="*" place="margin">Since the writing of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, &amp; when I was come to <hi>London</hi> about the Printing of it, I lighted by chance vpon D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iordans</hi> lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corſe of <hi>Naturall Bathes and Minerall wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he hath a peculiar o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the actuall heat of Minerall Water, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he aſcribeth to the <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation</hi> of Mineralls, and illuſtrateth the ſame with reaſons and examples. I am ſo farre from diſliking it, that I applaud it, and leaue both his and mine opinion to the choice of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for in thoſe abſtruſe things we haue no certaine knowledge, but onely probable conjectures. Howſoever, the leaſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of theſe two opinions is farre more likely, then thoſe imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary actuall fires, which the vulgar opinion holdeth.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now for the other Springs, which are actually cold, there are ſundry differences of them, according to the ſeverall ſubſtances they doe run through, and the nature and effects of ſome of them are very admirable. Some doe turne into ſtone whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is caſt into them, eſpecially if the things caſt in be or a looſe and <hi>porous</hi> ſubſtance, as leather, balls, gloues, and ſuch like; and <hi>Plinie</hi> and others deſcribe diverſe Springs of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>But not to goe out of this Iſland for examples, there is a Spring of that nature in <hi>Wales</hi> in a peece of ground belonging to Sir <hi>Thomas Middleton.</hi> And the quicke activi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſome of thoſe Springs is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16769:16"/>
and almoſt incredible; for <hi>Bodinus</hi> doth<note n="t" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> The. at. Nat.</note> affirme, that, he hath ſeene ſtickes of wood, ſtrawes, and ſuch like ſmall things converted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſtone in <hi>Lacu Piceno et Allienſi fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Avernorum,</hi> within the ſpace of two or three houres. So that <hi>Plinies</hi> aſſertion, who<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 35. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> ſaith, that earth is turned into ſtone in a fountaine of <hi>Gnidus</hi> within the ſpace of eight moneths, is no more to be wondred at. The ſame Author, namely, <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Li.</hi> 31. <hi>c</hi> 2.</note> maketh mention of two foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, the one called <hi>Cerone,</hi> which maketh the ſheepe, that drinke of it, to beare blacke wooll, and the other <hi>Melan,</hi> which maketh the wooll of the ſheepe, which drinke of it white, and if they drinke of both, their wooll will become of two colours; And of another called <hi>Crathis,</hi> which procureth whitneſſe, and of a fourth called <hi>Sibaris,</hi> which cauſeth black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the ſheepe and Oxen, which drinke of the ſame. Nay, the ſame
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16769:17"/>
effect is ſeene alſo in men, which drinke of them, for thoſe that drinke of <hi>Sibaris,</hi> become blacker, harder, and of a curled haire, and ſuch as drinke of <hi>Crathis</hi> waxe whiter, ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and of a ſmooth haire. He brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in alſo other Waters, which haue the like effect in changing the colour of ſuch as vſe them. He ſaith likewiſe, that there are two Springs in <hi>Baeotia,</hi> neere the river of <hi>Orchome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> whereof the one ſtrengtheneth memorie, and the other cauſes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion. A fountaine in <hi>Arcadia</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Linus</hi> preſerveth conception and hindreth aborſement, and on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, the river called <hi>Amphriſus</hi> maketh women barren. <hi>Cydnus,</hi> a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of <hi>Cilicia</hi> helpeth the Gowt in the feete, as appeareth by the Epiſtle of <hi>Caſsius Parmenſis</hi> to <hi>Marcus Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius;</hi> and contrariwiſe by the vſe of the Water, which is in <hi>Traezenen,</hi> all men get the Gowt in their feete. All ſuch as drinke of a lake called
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16769:17"/>
                  <hi>Clitorius,</hi> beginne thereby to hate wine. <hi>Polyclytus</hi> relateth, that the water of a fountaine in <hi>Cilicia</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in ſteade of Oyle; And <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtus,</hi> that the like is done by the water of a Spring in <hi>Aethiopia;</hi> and <hi>Lycus,</hi> that the water of a fountaine in <hi>India</hi> burneth in a Lampe. The like is alſo at <hi>Ecbatana. Iuba</hi> ſpeaketh of a Lake amongſt the <hi>Troglodytes,</hi> which for the hurt it doth, is called the mad-lake, and ſaith that it is bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſalt thrice in a day, and then freſh, and ſo againe at night. The ſame Author alſo maketh mention of a Spring in <hi>Arabia,</hi> which bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth vp with ſuch force, that it ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth forth whatſoever is throwne into it, though it be never ſo waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. There are two fountaines in <hi>Phrigia,</hi> the one called <hi>Claeon,</hi> and the other <hi>Gelon,</hi> having thoſe Greeke names from their effects, for the firſt maketh men cry, and the ſecond makes them laugh. There is an hot
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16769:18"/>
Spring at <hi>Cranon,</hi> and yet without exceſſiue hear, which being mingled with Wine, and kept in a veſſell, keepeth the ſame hot by the ſpace of three dayes. There is a river in <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynia</hi> called <hi>Olachas,</hi> into which if perjured perſons be throwne, they feele as much heate, as if they were in a flaming fire. In <hi>Cantabria</hi> there are three Springs but eight foote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder, which running together make a goodly river, and every one of them by turnes becommeth dry twelue times, and ſometimes twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie times a day, ſo that a man would thinke there were no more water in it, whileſt in the meane time his next neighbours be full, and flow conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually. There is a brooke in <hi>Iudea,</hi> which is dryed vp every Sabbath. In <hi>Macedonia,</hi> not farre from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher of <hi>Euripides,</hi> there are two brookes running together, the one having very wholeſome water, and the other poiſonous and deadly.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16769:18"/>
                  <hi>Quod ſi quis,</hi> ſaith<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 31 <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Plinie, fide carere ex his aliqua arbitratur, diſcat in nulla parte naturae majora eſſe miracula.</hi> If any man thinke, that ſome of theſe things are paſt beliefe, let him learne that there are no greater miracles in any other part of nature, than in Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. But if any man deſire to know more concerning the various nature and effects of Springs and Rivers, let him reade the thirteenth dialogue of <hi>Simon Majolus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Vultua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> in that Tome of his Workes, which he intitleth <hi>Dies Caniculares,</hi> and there he will finde wherewith to ſatisfie his curioſitie. I paſſe now to mineral and medicinable ſprings, which vſe to be drunke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER V.</hi> Of Minerall and Medicinable Springs.</head>
               <p>MInerall waters, by their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold turnings and wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings vnder the ground, are
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16769:19"/>
as it were <hi>impregnated</hi> with diverſe vertues and faculties of the ſeverall mineralls, through which they run, and draw with them, either the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, or ſubſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e of the ſame, and ſometimes both. And therefore as meere pureneſſe commendeth ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Springs and Wells, ſo doth the various mixture of ſeverall things, though ſomtimes of a contrary and repugnant nature, procure commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to medicinable waters. Some of them are beholding for whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they haue to the ſeverall kinds of earth, which they paſſe through, and licke, as it were, by the way, as <hi>Bole, Ocre, Rubricke, Chalke,</hi> and the like; Others to liquors or congea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led juyces, as, <hi>Allum, Bitumen, Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, Nitrum,</hi> Coperoſe; And others againe to Mettalls, as gold, ſilver, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, Copper, Tinne, Lead. There are ſome alſo, which owe their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues to ſtone, as Cryſtall, Marble, Pumice ſtone, <hi>Lapis Haematites,</hi> and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16769:19"/>
the like; and others to the roots of trees &amp; plants, though theſe be rare, either becauſe trees doe not roote ſo deepe, or by reaſon that medicina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſprings are commonly in barren ſoyles, as on the contrary whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever there is a fruitfull ſoyle, there are no minerall or medicinable ſprings to be found. Out of all theſe ſubterraneall ſubſtances di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe ſprings draw ſometimes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary faculties, or at leaſt ſuch as haue but ſmall affinitie one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and from hence it happeneth that oftentimes one &amp; the ſame me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinable ſpring cureth diverſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, which are either contrary one to another, or at leaſt haue but ſmall affinitie together. It is of this as it is of Theriake or Mithridate, which are compoſitions co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſting of a great number of ſimples of contrary and repugnant natures, as it were hudled together by chance; and yet when thoſe compoſitions haue had their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16769:20"/>
due <hi>fermentation,</hi> and that thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall ſimples haue wrought one vpon another, and become to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated together, there reſulteth afterwards an vniverſal forme in the compoſition, which maketh it excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent for moſt diſeaſes, and as it were a generall <hi>Panpharmacon.</hi> And in that regard ſome doe merrily call Mithridate the father, and Treacle the mother of all medicines. But that we may the more accurately di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt minerall Springs, we muſt conſider the nature of the mineralls, and looke which of them haue affinitie together, &amp; which not. <hi>Bitumen, Salt, Sulphur, Coperoſe Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> are hot, and therefore they haue a facultie to cut, cleanſe, open, dry, extenuate, and diſperſe.<note n="z" place="margin">Lib. <hi>5.</hi> de Metallici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Albertus Magnus,</hi> and after him <hi>Andernacus</hi> and others, doe reckon <hi>Sal nitrum</hi> with theſe, and hold it to be hot, which might be granted them, if by <hi>nitrum</hi> they vnderſtood that <hi>nitrum,</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:16769:20"/>
whereof<note n="a" place="margin">Lib. de aere locis et aquis.</note> 
                  <hi>Hippocrates,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 89.</note> 
                  <hi>Dioſcorides,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 31. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Plinie,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Lib. <hi>9.</hi> Simp. Medicam.</note> 
                  <hi>Galen</hi> doe ſpeake; But I doe not thinke that either <hi>Albertus</hi> or <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernacus</hi> ever ſaw it, becauſe it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be ſcantie &amp; hard to be found in the time of thoſe ancient Authors before cited after <hi>Hippocrates.</hi> But our Saltpeter, which is now called <hi>Nitrum</hi> amongſt vs, is as farre from that ancient <hi>Nitrum,</hi>
               </p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">Quantum Hipanis veneto diſsitus Eridano.</q>
               <p>For if gunpowder were not enough to proue the coldneſſe of <hi>Nitrum,</hi> in which its oppoſition and contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to Brimſtone is ſo manifeſt, yet were the <hi>Sal prunellae</hi> of the <hi>Chymiſts</hi> (which is nothing but <hi>Nitrum</hi> puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from its dregs with <hi>Flores ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phuris</hi>) ſufficient to evince it, a very little of it put into a glaſſe of Wine, making it ſo cold, that one is ſcarce able to drinke it. And to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16769:21"/>
I remember that when I was in <hi>Holland,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Orenge, Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice,</hi> was wont alwayes in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time to haue ſome of it throwne into the water, where his Wine lay a cooling. That <hi>Sal prunellae</hi> alſo is the beſt remedie againſt the heate, drineſſe, &amp; roughneſſe of the tongue in all feavers, and eſpecially in that <hi>Hungarian</hi>-feaver called <hi>Prunella,</hi> from that ſymptome, which gaue likewiſe the name of <hi>Sal prunellae</hi> to that purified <hi>Nitrum,</hi> by reaſon of the excellency of it in aſſwaging the ſame. And the more to confirme this, one of the foure ſprings of the <hi>Spa</hi> called <hi>Tounelet,</hi> and conſiſting chiefly of <hi>Nitrum,</hi> is ſo very cold, both in the mouth, and in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, that few can endure it, and in that regard it is very little fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented; and during my ſtay there I doe not remember that I ever ſaw at it more then a <hi>Capuchin</hi> friar, and another Clergie man, who vſed it
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16769:21"/>
for the heate of their livers; in which caſe it may doe good, if the ſtomack be not too weake.</p>
               <p>Silver, Iron, Tinne, Lead, are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted cold, and by reaſon of their aſtringencie, to be at leaſt in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond degree. Gold is likewiſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced amongſt theſe, though a man might perhaps with better right ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it temperate. Now in regard of this varietie, ſome ſprings are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Nitrous, Sulphurous, Bituminous, Aluminous,</hi> &amp;c. according to the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or predomina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t minerall, of which they doe participate. But yet ſome there are, in which it is a very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult matter to know the ſame. So the <hi>Vberlingunians</hi> in <hi>Suevia</hi> doe diſpute to this day, whether their minerall Spring proceed of Lead or Copper. In like manner, the <hi>Italians</hi> are not well agreed whether the vertue of the mineral water about <hi>Lucca</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from Iron or from Allum. And a great man, that was one of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16769:22"/>
chiefeſt Chymiſts of this age, doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted whether he ſhould call the <hi>Emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſes Aquae Aluminous</hi> or <hi>Nitrous;</hi> ſo hard a thing it is exactly to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh in things, that are compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and permixt. But it is now time we ſhould goe to <hi>Tunbridge</hi> water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER VI.</hi> Of <hi>Tunbridge</hi> Water.</head>
               <p>THe water commonly knowne here amongſt vs by the name of <hi>Tunbridge</hi> water, are two ſmall Springs contiguous together, about ſome foure miles Southward from the towne of <hi>Tunbridge</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> from which they haue their name, as being the neareſt Towne in <hi>Kent</hi> to them. They are ſeated in a valley compaſſed about with ſtony hills, ſo barren, that there groweth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16769:22"/>
but heath vpon the ſame. Iuſt there doe <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Suſſex</hi> meete, and one may with leſſe than halfe a breath runne from thoſe Springs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It pleaſed our gracious Queene <hi>Marie</hi> to grace this Water by her preſence two yeares agoe, ſo that thoſe Springs may juſtly be called, as ſome doe call them now, <hi>Queene Maries Wells.</hi> The taſte of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is not vnpleaſant to thoſe, who haue a while beene vſed to it, and it is a ſure thing, that no man is able to drinke halfe ſo much of any other liquor, though never ſo pleaſant vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, as he may of this. What o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mineralls it runneth through, beſides Iron and the <hi>rubrick</hi> of Iron, which is ſeene on the ground, over which the water runneth, is not yet well knowne, for there hath beene as yet no digging neare about the ſame. The greater part of thoſe that drinke of it, are purged by ſtoole,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16769:23"/>
and ſome by vomit, as well as by v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, which perhaps ſhould argue ſome other mineralls, beſides Iron. The ſame may peradventure be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered in after times. Howſoever though there were no other mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls thereabout, beſides Iron, yet Iron being a mettall, and all mettals, according to the Chymicks, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of two principles, <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> whereſoever there are any mettalls bred, there muſt alſo of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie their principles be.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, all mettalls haue alſo their peculiar ſalts, and Iron in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular hath a great deale of <hi>volatill</hi> ſalt, which is it that diſſolveth in the <hi>Chalybeate</hi> wine now ſo much in vſe. Now Iron is of an aſtringent and corroborating facultie, and hath an opening vertue withall, as may be ſeene by the powder of ſteele (ſteele being nothing but a <hi>defecated</hi> Iron) which is vſed with good ſucceſſe in the greene ſickneſſe, and in all other
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16769:23"/>
diſeaſes proceeding from obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But here I ſhall ſeeme perhaps to ſome to contradict my ſelfe, in making Iron both aſtringent and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening, which the vulgar thinke to be two qualities inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>patible in one ſubject, and yet they are deceived, for to open and corroborate haue no ſuch repugnance, but that they are together in many Simples. Now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning thoſe two Springs, a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion doth often ariſe amongſt thoſe who are there a drinking, which of them ſhould be the better and ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but being ſo contiguous and neare together, certainly there can be no manifeſt ods betwixt them, and though I often taſted of both immediately one after the other, yet can I not ſay, that I ever found any perceptible difference betwixt them. Yet will I not denie, but that it may ſo fall out, that at ſome times the one may appeare ſtronger than the other, according as the Water
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16769:24"/>
may participate more of the vertue of the mineralls at one time, than at another; But I thinke that there can be nothing conſtant in it, though they may alternatiuely ſomething differ one from another. This ſhall ſuffice to haue beene ſpoken concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoſe Springs. It followeth now that we make an enumeration of the chiefeſt diſeaſes their water may be vſed for, wherein wee will chiefly follow experience, ſeeing it is an empiricall remedy, &amp; yet ſo, as we ſhall not exclude reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it it be <hi>empericum remedium,</hi> yet muſt we not vſe it altogether empirically, nor make it a <hi>Panpharmacon,</hi> or a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacea,</hi> a medicine for all diſeaſes, and ſend thither promiſcuouſly all ſorts of Patients, as ſome Phyſitians doe to the like Springs, when they are at a <hi>nonplus</hi> with them, and after a long time can doe no good vpon them in <hi>Chronicall</hi> diſeaſes; For then they ſend them to thoſe minerall waters,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16769:24"/>
                  <hi>tanquam ad ſacram anchoram.</hi> Which cauſeth thoſe Springs to become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous, and to looſe the credit they juſtly deſerue (the common people ordinarily judging of things by the event) when ſome miſcarry after the vſe of the ſame, either becauſe they were alreadie too farre ſpent when they were ſent thither, or by reaſon their diſeaſes were not to be cured by that remedie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER VII.</hi> The chiefeſt diſeaſes, againſt which <hi>Tunbridge</hi> water may be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with good ſucceſſe.</head>
               <p>BEing now to reckon vp the chiefeſt diſeaſes, which <hi>Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> water is good for, wee will not goe <hi>a capite ad calcem,</hi> from the head to the heele, but beginne at that, which it is moſt generally good for, and that is obſtructions, which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16769:25"/>
are the cauſes of infinite diſeaſes. This water then doth effectually o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen all manner of obſtructions, whereſoever they be lurking, and eſpecially the obſtructions of the <hi>meſaraicall</hi> veines, of the ſpleene, and of the liver, and that better, then any <hi>Apozemes</hi> or other phyſick whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. For thoſe obſtructions being ſtubborne, and requiring a great deale of Phyſick to be removed, and Phyſicke being both loathſome and chargeable, people grow weary of it, before a Phyſitian ſhall haue run a quarter of the courſe, which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the remooving of thoſe obſtructions; and that is the reaſon that ſo many are troubled with <hi>chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall</hi> lingering diſeaſes, which in their owne nature are not incurable; but onely remaine vncured, either becauſe the Patient is not able or willing to vndergoe ſuch a courſe of Phyſicke, as is requiſite for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, or becauſe hee loveth his
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16769:25"/>
purſe too well. But theſe Waters bring no charges, and after one hath beene vſed a little while to them, the taking of them is not trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome at all, but the longer a man continueth the vſe of them, the more he may, and being taken in a large quantitie, they cannot chuſe but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen effectually. Wherefore they are of excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vſe for all diſeaſes, which haue their dependencie vpon ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, as all long and tedious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, quartanes, and the like; for a dropſie, the blacke &amp; yeallow jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, the <hi>Schirrhus Lienis,</hi> or hard ſwelling of the ſpleene, which the common people call an ague cake, the ſcurvie, the greene ſickneſſe, the whites in women, and the defect and exceſſe of their courſes. And albeit this laſt aſſertion ſeemeth to haue ſome repugnancie, in that we aſcribe two contrary effects to one and the ſame agent, yet there is no ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for the one is done by opening
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16769:26"/>
of obſtructions, and the other either by cooling the bloud, when it is too hot and ſharpe, and ſo provoketh nature to expulſion, or by corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating &amp; ſtrengthning the retentiue facultie. And it is the propertie of all equivocall agents to varie their operations according to the varietie of their objects, and of the matter they worke vpon; ſo the Sunne mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Waxe, and hardeneth Clay. This water doth alſo cut and exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate tough, clammy, and (if I may ſo ſpeake) <hi>Tartarean</hi> flegme, and in that regard it may be much availa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for thoſe, who are vſed to be troubled with the Colicke, when ſuch an humor is contained in their gutts.</p>
               <p>It ſcowreth and cleanſeth all the paſſages of vrine, and therefore is good againſt the gravell &amp; the ſtone in the kidneyes, <hi>Vreteres</hi> or bladder, where alſo it diſſolveth and waſheth away a kinde of clammy flegmatick
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16769:26"/>
excreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bred in the bladder, which ſometimes ſtopping the paſſage of ones water, maketh him beleeue that he is troubled with the ſtone; as happened to one, that was himſelfe a very skilful and famous ſtone-cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who being fully perſwaded that he had a ſtone in his bladder, gaue himſelfe to another of the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be cut at <hi>Namurs;</hi> But when he was cut, nothing was found in his bladder, but ſuch a tough humour, which might haue beene diſſolved and voyded with facilitie by the helpe of the <hi>Spa</hi> water, which was but a dayes journey from him. It is good alſo (in regard of the aſtringent and healing facultie it hath) for all inward vlcers, and eſpecially for thoſe of the kidneyes and bladder, and of the <hi>Muſculus ſphinater,</hi> which openeth and ſhutteth the ſame. And in confirmation thereof divers haue bin cured of a bloudy vrine, which had long troubled them, &amp; amongſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16769:27"/>
the reſt a worthy <hi>Kentiſh</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, with whom I went thither the laſt yeare.</p>
               <p>It is good alſo againſt all invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>Dyſenteries</hi> or bloudy Flixes: as alſo all other Fluxes of the belly, whether it be <hi>Leienteria, Diarrhaea,</hi> or <hi>Fluxus hepaticus.</hi> It doth likewiſe extinguiſh all inward inflamations and hot diſtempers, and yet for all that the ſtomacke is no whit hurt by the actuall coldneſſe thereof, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther corroborated and ſtrengthned, and appetite provoked, yea in ſome but too much, as in my ſelfe for one; For whenſoever I dranke either at the <hi>Spa</hi> or at <hi>Tunbridg,</hi> I was never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to faſt with patience vntill noon, but muſt needs <hi>offam latranti ſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho offerre,</hi> caſt a bit to my barking ſtomack, before the reſt of my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany went to dinner. For this cauſe when I was at the <hi>Spa,</hi> a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, who was come thither with the yong Prince <hi>Doria</hi> (who was then
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16769:27"/>
but a youth) would not let him take the water aboue two or three dayes, when he ſaw ſuch an effect in him, fearing that he would receiue more hurt by the exceſſe of his appetite, than benefit by the water; and ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a long and troubleſome journey from <hi>Italy</hi> thither, he returned home without any profit. The <hi>nerues</hi> or ſinewes, and the originall of them, the braine, are ſtrengthened by the vſe of this water, and conſequently it is good againſt the palſie, inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to an apoplexy, lethargie, and ſuch like diſeaſes of the head.</p>
               <p>And ſome <hi>Paralyticks</hi> haue beene ſeene, who ſometimes voyded all their water by vrine, and at other times were as effectually purged, as if they had taken a ſtrong potion, and withall ſweated aboundantly all their body over. All theſe eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuations, and vomitting alſo, are ſometimes ſeene in other diſeaſes, as well as in that; Nay beſides that in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16769:28"/>
ſome women you ſhall haue an eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation by vrine, <hi>&amp; per menſes ſimul &amp; haemorrhoidas.</hi> The cauſe of all Rheumes and Diſtillations is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe remooved by the helpe of this water, and all diſeaſes cured, which haue their dependencie vpon the ſame, for all that verſe of <hi>Schola Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lernitana,</hi>
                  <q xml:lang="lat">Iejunes, vigiles, ſitias, ſic rheumata cures.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Convulſions alſo, Head-ach, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graine, &amp; Vertigo, are driven away by the vſe of the ſame, if the patient be conſtant and not too ſoone wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Againſt vomitting and the hic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kot, it is vſed with good ſucceſſe. Thoſe that are troubled with <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chondriacall</hi> melancholie find a great deale of eaſe by this water. It hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth alſo the running of the reines, whether it be <hi>Gonorrhea ſimplex</hi> or <hi>Venerea,</hi> and the diſtemper of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtatae</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:16769:28"/>
ariſing from thence, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a certaine carnoſitie, which groweth ſometimes in the conduite of the vrine, nay and the Poxe alſo, the water having a notable potenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all drying facultie. It driveth away beſides all manner of wormes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be ordinary ones, or <hi>aſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rides</hi> or <hi>taeniae.</hi> It may be vſed alſo for the Gowt, but it muſt be with ſome caution, and the body muſt be extraordinarily well prepared and purged before, becauſe it hath ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times brought the fit vpon ſome, who were well when they came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Outwardly applied it doth helpe ſore eyes, red pimples, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther externall infirmities. More diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, which haue affinity with theſe, it may be vſed for, but I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelfe with this enumeration of the aforeſaid ones, and paſſe to the time, manner, and order of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the water. Yet muſt I not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get in the behalfe of women, to tell
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16769:29"/>
them that there is nothing better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt barrenneſſe, and to make them fruitfull, if other good and fitting meanes, ſuch as the ſeverall cauſes ſhall require, be joyned with the water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER VIII.</hi> Of the time, manner, and order of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Tunbridge</hi> Water.</head>
               <p>SOme that ſhall reade the next foregoing Chapter, will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſay, that I make this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a direct <hi>Panpharmacon,</hi> a remedie for all diſeaſes, and therefore wiil giue ſmall credite vnto it. But for all that, daily experience doth, and if it continue to be vſed, will more and more confirme what I haue ſaid to be true. For very few of thoſe, who liue at the <hi>Spa</hi> (whoſe Water hath great affinitie with that of <hi>Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi>)
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16769:29"/>
and in the Country about it, and make that Water their ordinary drinke, as many doe, and my ſelfe haue ſeene there very aged people, that did never drinke any thing elſe; few of them, I ſay, are troubled with headach, heart-burning, ſtone, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of the kidneyes, liver, or ſpleene, falling ſickneſſe, &amp; the like, and as for the Iaundiſe, Dropſie, and Scabbes, they doe not know what they are. My ſelfe during my ſtay there being once rid out to take the ayre with a couple of Gentlemen, and a ſhowre of raine comming, we made to a Countrey houſe neare hand to ſhelter our ſelues, and after the taking of a Pipe of Tobacco, I requeſted the goodman of the houſe (who was a very old man, and yet freſh and luſtie, and with very few gray haires) to giue vs a cup of his beere, but he anſwered me, that he never had had any beere in his houſe, if we would drinke good <hi>Pouhon,</hi> it
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16769:30"/>
was at our ſervice, and he had a freſh veſſell of it abroach. <hi>Pouhon</hi> is the name of that Spring of the <hi>Spa,</hi> which ſtandeth in the middle of the Towne, and by the ſame name they call alſo the Water thereof. But to returne to our matter,
<q xml:lang="lat">
                     <l>Temporibus medicina valet, data tempore proſunt,</l>
                     <l>Et data non apto tempore, vina no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</l>
                  </q>
and ſo water. The time then of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thoſe waters, is either the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the yeare, when to come to them, or the time of the day, when to drinke of the ſame, Concerning the ſeaſon of the yeare, Sommer is the fitteſt, when there is a ſettled warme and dry weather, as in the dog dayes eſpecially.</p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">Cùm Canis arentes findit hiulcus agros.</q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:16769:30"/>And the chiefeſt moneths be <hi>Iune, Iuly, Anguſt,</hi> and <hi>September,</hi> although the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who naturally loue good Beere and Wine better than Water, vſe to haue this riming verſe in their mouthes,</p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">Menſibus in quibus R. non debes bibere Water.</q>
               <p>And according as the yeare proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, a man may ſometimes come ſooner, and continue later. In ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, whenſoever the weather is cleare and dry, the water is then beſt, as well in Winter, as in Summer, yea in hard froſtie weather the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is commonly ſtrongeſt, the <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periſtaſis</hi> of the ayre hindering that there is not ſo great an evaporation of the minerall ſpirits of the Water. For when the weather is rainy or miſty, and that <hi>Iupiter</hi> doth <hi>per cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum mingere,</hi> piſſe through a ſieue, as <hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> merrily ſpeakes, the
<pb facs="tcp:16769:31"/>
water looſeth much of its vertue, My ſelfe haue knowne at the <hi>Spa</hi> a Friar of the reformed order of Saint <hi>Frauncis,</hi> a good honeſt temperate man, who aſſured me, that having beene there three whole yeares to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether continually for the ſtone (of which he ſhewed me a boxe almoſt full, of ſeverall formes and bigneſſe) and taking the Water all the while, both ſommer and winter, when the weather was ſeaſonable, he found divers times the water better, ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and of a more ſpeedy paſſage in froſtie weather, then in the middle of Sommer, without ever percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any inconvenience by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, no more at that time, then in Sommer, for all he did alwayes drinke it cold.</p>
               <p>For ſome that vſe to take it in cold weather, doe warme it, but ſure the water cannot chuſe by that meanes but looſe a great deale of its vertue, which in the warming evaporateth
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16769:31"/>
away, ſeeing that in the very tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting of it, the ſame doth happen. When the <hi>Spa</hi> water is bottled to be ſent away, albeit thoſe who haue the charge of it, be never ſo carefull in ſtopping the Bottles cloſe with boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Corke, and pitching them over, yet will the minerall ſpirits finde way, in ſo much, as when you come to open them, you ſhall ſtill finde ſome want, and ſometimes a prettie deale, eſpecially of the water of the <hi>Savenier,</hi> which is more ſubtile and ſpirituall, than that of <hi>Pouhon.</hi> But to returne to the matter, there is no more to be ſaid, but that in a word the Water is alwayes beſt when the weather is cleareſt and drieſt.</p>
               <p>Now concerning the time of the day, the morning, when the Sunne is an houre more or leſſe, high, is the fitteſt time to drinke the water. For when the Sunne beginneth to be of force, it doth attract ſome of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſpirits, and the water looſeth
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16769:32"/>
ſome of its ſtrength; and betimes in the morning it is alſo beſt walking. And you are ſo to drinke the water, as you may haue taken the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which you intend to take that day, within as ſmall a ſpace of time, as conveniently you can, without oppreſſing your ſtomack too much, as within an houre, or leſſe, if you be able. Thoſe that lye not too very farre from the Springs, and are able to vſe their legges, ſhall doe better to come thither afoote, than to ride, becauſe ſo they ſhall heate their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies more. Yet doe I not intend they ſhould be ſo hot, as to ſweate, or to be readie to ſweate, for that would doe hurt, but I meane onely that their naturall heate ſhould be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing awaked and excited, becauſe then the water will be the better at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, and haue the more ſpeedie paſſage. After every glaſſe, or every two or three glaſſes, according as you ſhall be able to take it, it will be
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16769:32"/>
good to take a few <hi>Carraway</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, or <hi>Coriander</hi>-ſeede, ſome <hi>Galin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, Zedoar, Elycampane, Angelica</hi>-roote, or ſuch like, to helpe the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion and paſſage of the Water. In ſome it is neceſſary, that they ſhould haue ſome <hi>Electuary, Lozen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> or the like, appropriated to the griefe, for which they take the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>Diverſe doe take Tobacco after their water, which I doe not diſlike, eſpecially if they hold it a good while in their mouthes, before they puffe it out. Moderate exerciſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is very available, but I vtterly diſlike it, if it be too violent, as run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, leaping, jumping, as ſome in wantonneſſe vſe to doe. For that kinde of exerciſe is rather a hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, than a helpe, to the digeſting of their water, and many times all the good it doth, is to bring it vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, weakening by that meanes their ſtomacke, which in vomitting
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16769:33"/>
doth alwayes ſuffer. True it is that if the ſtomacke be foule, it is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe ſometimes ſo to doe, and I am not againſt it. After you haue taken your full quantitie, it will doe well to walke and ſtirre there vp and downe, and to compoſe your ſelfe to mirth with the reſt of the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie; For thoſe that looke to reape benefit by <hi>Tunbridge,</hi> muſt turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all cares and melancholy.</p>
               <p>In your returne to your lodging, I hold it better to ride, than to goe afoote, becauſe ſitting vpon your horſe, the inward parts, as the <hi>muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles</hi> of the belly, the guttes, and the ſtomacke it ſelfe are thereby borne vp and contracted, and by the jog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the horſe moderately ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſo conſequently your wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will be the better digeſted. The ſigne of the through-concoction of the ſame is commonly when your vrine beginneth to haue a <hi>tincture</hi> and to be coloured, and then may
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16769:33"/>
you goe to dinner; But of this wee will ſpeake of purpoſe when wee come vpon diet. I ſaide before, that the beſt time of the day to take the water was betimes in the morning, and I meane alſo it ſhould be the onely time for that day. For I haue knowne ſome, who tooke it twice a day, namely, in the afternoone alſo, but I could never approue of it, and my reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, that if they take it ſoone after dinner, their meate will not be digeſted, and the water forcing to make way for it ſelfe, will draw with it the <hi>Chylus</hi> raw and vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted, and ſo cauſe crudities and obſtructions, which will doe a great deale more hurt, than the water can doe them good; And if they take it later after dinner, their water will not bee digeſted before Supper. Once a day then is enough, leaſt you haue worſe ſpeede by making too much haſte. Now for the whole quantitie of the water to be taken in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16769:34"/>
one morning, it is a thing, which cannot juſtly be defined, in regard of the difference of bodies in age, ſexe, ſtrength, and other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; But generally thoſe that are able to drinke moſt, receiue the moſt benefit, ſo that they doe digeſt and voyde their water well. And here it is, if any where, that the Greeke Proverbe ſhould take place, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>aut bibe, aut abi,</hi> either drinke, or be gone; If you cannot tipple, this is no place for you. Yet muſt every man ever haue this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rule in memorie, <hi>a juvantibus &amp; laedentibus optima judicatio,</hi> the beſt judication or direction is from thoſe things, which doe good, and from ſuch as doe hurt. You ſhall ſee ſome that ariſe to a great quantitie, and <q xml:lang="lat">Invenies illic, qui Neſtoris ebibat annos,</q>
               </p>
               <p>Three hundred ounces, according
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:16769:34"/>
to <hi>Neſtors</hi> yeares. Yea, and ſome a greater quantitie. And it is a thing, that will make the very wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there filling the glaſſes to laugh, to ſee ſome patients ſent thither by igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Phyſitians, and appointed to take ten or twelue ounces of water, and ariſe perhaps to twentie or thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ounces. But this may be a rule for a body of competent yeares and ſtrength to beginne at thirtie, fortie, or fiftie ounces, and to ariſe by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, increaſing their quantitie eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, to an hundreth, an hundreth and fiftie, or two hundred ounces, more or leſſe, as they ſhall be able, and ſo againe to decline and decreaſe by degrees, ending were they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, when they are to leaue the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>As for the time of every mans ſtay there, it is a thing which cannot be defined; for in ſome diſeaſes ſome weekes ſuffice, in others diverſe months are not enough, nay in ſome
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16769:35"/>
they haue neede to come thither the next yeare, and the next to that too. This I hope will ſuffice for the time, manner, and order of taking <hi>Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> water, I will now paſſe to the preparation of the body of ſuch as are to take it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER IX.</hi> Of the preparation of the body of ſuch as are to take the Water.</head>
               <p>I Haue ſet downe before the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt diſeaſes, which may be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the helpe of this water, but I am not ſo to be vnderſtood, as though I meant that the water alone were ſufficient for the ſame in all of them, without any other helpes. For albeit this be an <hi>empiricall</hi> reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, yet muſt it not be vſed altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>empirically,</hi> but with reaſon, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16769:35"/>
and circumſpection, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe hurt, rather than good, will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the vſe of it. Many haue falne into diſeaſes, as feavers and agues, by comming vnadviſedly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared to thoſe waters, although, as we ſaid before, there is nothing better for agues, then they are, if they be rightly and adviſedly vſed, the body being firſt prepared and purged. For although bloud by a ſole diſtemper of heate may cauſe a feaver, yet cannot the other humors doe it, as<note n="e" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de diff. febrium.</note> 
                  <hi>Galen</hi> well obſerveth, vnleſſe they putrifie, which they will not doe if the body be free from obſtructions, and <hi>perſpirable,</hi> and therefore that body, which is to be taken with an ague, muſt firſt be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed. Now theſe waters being very <hi>diureticall,</hi> when they meete with a foule body, having a repleti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of groſſe humors, they eaſily and ſpeedily carry the ſame with them into the veines, which not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16769:36"/>
to giue paſſage to ſuch a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of humors, they are thereby ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed and ſtopped, and thoſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors being there retained and wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in, and not <hi>perflated or ventilated,</hi> they inflame and putrifie, and ſo produce a <hi>putride</hi> feaver or ague. Wherefore thoſe that loue their health and life, muſt before they vſe the water, if they haue not a very pure body, prepare and purge the ſame to prevent all inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>Now according as bodies doe differ in ſexe, age, temperature, qualitie of the <hi>peccant</hi> humour, and other circumſtances, ſo muſt they accordingly diverſly be prepared and purged. And in that regard we haue not thought it good to ſet downe here any formes thereof, but referre thoſe that ſhall come to the water, to the adviſe and counſell of learned and skilfull Phyſitions, and ſuch as are withall well acquainted
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16769:36"/>
with thoſe kinde of waters, which is the maine point. And as for thoſe, that come farre off, they may take Phyſicke at <hi>Tunbridge,</hi> and it will be beſt for them ſo to doe, becauſe if they take Phyſicke before, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently travell vpon the ſame, it may produce ſome danger.</p>
               <p>If the reſort to the Water conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, and that there be competent company at the ſame, I doe purpoſe by the grace of God to be there e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Sommer (for it is a place I like) and if any be pleaſed to conferre with me, I will be readie to afford them my beſt counſell; and they ſhall finde there varietie of Phyſicke appropriated to the ſeverall diſeaſes which the Water is to be vſed for. Neither is it enough to prepare the body and take Phyſick before com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Water, but it is requiſite alſo, in ſome diſeaſes, to take ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing now and then during the time they vſe the Water, to helpe the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:16769:37"/>
working of it, and to cauſe a happie and proſperous effect by the ſame, and ſo much the more, becauſe ſome are not able, either by reaſon of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, or otherwiſe, to ſtay there a competent time, and therefore haue need of ſome other helpe. For ſome diſeaſes are ſo ſtubborne and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to be eradicated, that we muſt fight at all weapons againſt the ſame, and yet all little enough too. Some vnlookt for accidents alſo happen there ſometimes, which haue neede to be redreſſed and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen by other meanes. But of theſe things neither my ſelfe, nor any man elſe, can ſpeake but in generall termes, and therefore I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, and paſſe to the dyet requiſite to be obſerved there.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:16769:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER X.</hi> Of the Dyet to be obſerved by thoſe that vſe <hi>Tunbridge</hi> Water.</head>
               <p>DYet amongſt Phyſitians is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in a larger ſignification, than it is with the vulgar, for beſides meate and drinke, it compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth ayre, motion, and quiet, things retained and voyded, ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and watching, and the paſſions of the minde. All theſe muſt be rightly ordered, both to preſerue, and to reſtore health. As for ayre, it muſt be taken ſuch as it is found there, and I thinke there is no great exception to be taken againſt it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereabout pure and wholeſome enough. Of motion and quiet wee haue ſaid ſomething before, when we ſpake of exerciſe, as alſo of the paſſions of the minde, when we wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed all ſuch as come to the Water,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16769:38"/>
to compoſe and frame themſelues to mirth, and to leaue all cares and melancholy at home. Concerning ſleeping &amp; watching, a moderation muſt be obſerved therein, though it be better to ſleepe ſomething too much, then to watch too long, and therefore you ſhall doe well to Sup betimes, and to goe to bed betimes, <hi>animo ſecuro, quieto &amp; libero,</hi> that the firſt, ſecond, and third concoction may be ended, before you take the water. And as for things voyded and retained, you muſt endevour to haue the benefite of nature by all manner of ordinary evacuations, as by ſtoole and vrine, and the private excrements of the braine, at the mouth and noſe. And thus much in briefe concerning thoſe things, wee will now come to meate and drinke. Bread is commonly, and with moſt men, the chiefeſt part of foode, and therefore though alwayes, yet here more eſpecially, you muſt haue a
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:16769:38"/>
care to haue bread of good pure wheate, well handled and ſeaſoned in the making, and well baked; For the excrements &amp; ill humors, which are heaped by the vſe of ill bread, are worſe than thoſe, which proceed from meate. Ravell bread generally is wholeſomer, than manchet, and not ſo apt to breede obſtructions, having ſome of the branne left in it, which is <hi>detergent,</hi> and maketh it paſſe the better. As for meate, let every one feede vpon that, which he hath beene moſt vſed to, ſo it be good meate, yeelding good nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of eaſie digeſtion; and let him ſhunne the vſe of ſawces, which haue much butter &amp; ſpices in them. For it was a good admonition of <hi>Diſarius,</hi> a learned Phyſitian, in<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Saturn.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Macrobius, Vitandos eſſe cibos, qui vltra ſitim &amp; famem appetentiam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducerent,</hi> that thoſe meates were to be avoyded, which did lengthen appetite beyond hunger and thirſt.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:16769:39"/>
If you can, be you contented with one diſh at a meale, for <hi>multa fercula multos morbos ferunt,</hi> many diſhes bring many diſeaſes, and <hi>pernicioſa ſentina eſt abdomen inſaturabile,</hi> an vnſatiable belly is a pernicious ſinke. In foule bodies eſpecially, over-fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding doth a great deale of hurt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Aphoriſme of<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The more you nouriſh foule bodies, the more you hurt them. In a word, a moderate ſober dyet is alwayes beſt, but eſpecially here. As for the kinds of meate, albeit amongſt the fleſh of fourefooted beaſts, Porke and Veale be chiefly commended in our bookes, yet here in regard of their moiſture, I preferre Mutton before them. And if Porke be to be avoyded, much more Pigge, Lambe, and ſuch like flaſhy meate. As for Beefe, though it be diſcommended by moſt Authors, yet good Beefe,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:16769:39"/>
well fed, and of an indifferent age, may be vſed without ſcruple, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by ſuch as haue beene accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to it, for thoſe Authors were never acquainted with our Engliſh Beefe. If Oxen indeede be killed when they are ſo olde, that they be paſt labour, their fleſh cannot be wholeſome, nor is to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. But for our good ſucculent Beefe here, I verily thinke, that if thoſe Authors were aliue againe, and ſhould taſte of it, they would be ſo farre from forbidding it, that to the contrary they would commend it. For if they doe ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend Veale, I ſee no reaſon they can haue to diſcommend good ſuccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Beefe.</p>
               <p>Beſides Mutton and Beefe, you may ſometimes haue Capons, Hens, Pullets, Chickens, Pigeons, Partridges, Pheaſants, black-birds, and other ſmall birds, Rabets, and the like. And becauſe ſome Hares
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:16769:40"/>
are ſometimes caught about <hi>Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> it is a queſtion, which ſome aske, whether thoſe who are there at the waters, may feed vpon them. They are growne infamous and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from moſt Tables vndeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly, out of a conceit that they are melancholy meate. But I will now take their cauſe in hand, and <hi>vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> them from that imputation, if I can, ſaying with <hi>Martial,</hi> 
                  <q xml:lang="lat">
                     <l>Inter aves turdus, ſi quis, me Iudice, certet,</l>
                     <l>Inter quadrupedes gloria prima lepus.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And leaſt I ſeeme to giue too eaſie an aſſent to the Poet, (though he was not a meere Poet, but well grounded in naturall Philoſophie) I will ſtriue to proue, that it is not melancholy meate, but meate for melancholy men.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I will bring in<note n="h" place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> de alim.</note> 
                  <hi>Galen</hi> to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trocinate
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:16769:40"/>
vnto him, who preferres the bloud of a Hare, before that of Hens, Pigeons, and all other birds, and ſaith that it is moſt ſweete and daintie. Now if Hares bloud be ſo good, how can the fleſh thereof be nought, which is made and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by it, fleſh being nothing elſe but bloud <hi>coagulated</hi> and converted into the ſame?</p>
               <p>The ſame Author<note n="i" place="margin">Ibidem ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio libri.</note> ſaith alſo, that Hares fleſh breedeth better bloud, than Mutton or Beefe. And if theſe two come every day to the Tables even of the nobleſt and richeſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, why ſhould the poore Hare, which is better, and yeeldeth better nouriſhment then they, be baniſhed from the ſame?</p>
               <p>After <hi>Galen,</hi> learned <hi>Heurnius</hi> rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koneth Hares fleſh in the firſt place amongſt thoſe meates, which alter melancholy in the kidneyes, but to alter and free from melancholy, and to breede melancholy, cannot both
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:16769:41"/>
be done by one kinde of meate. For if any man would flie here to ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſubſtance, or to an hidden propertie, he ſhould deſerue to be hiſſed at. But they ſay it is a melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly fearefull creature. What rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they haue to call him ſo, vnleſſe it be becauſe he ſhunneth &amp; runneth away from the dogs, which purſue him, I doe not know; But if that be all, doe not Wolues, Bulls, Beares, yea and Lyons alſo, the like? If wee may beleeue thoſe, who haue beene in <hi>Africa,</hi> an old woman there, or a childe with a ſticke in their hands doe driue away Lyons, as wee doe dogs here. And a Hare is not ſo fearefull, but that you ſhall ſee ſome of them turne about, and looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the dogs after a daring manner. They doe not lye in holes and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, as Conies doe, which in that regard ſhould be more melancholy, and yet they are in moſt common vſe amongſt vs, and accounted the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16769:41"/>
beſt meate. And as for their foode, it is the ſame with that of Partrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the excellencie whereof is no where controverted, and with the vſe of them onely the Poxe may be cured, as <hi>Cardan</hi> holdeth, who could ſpeake of it by experience, as having had that diſeaſe ſeven times, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe witneſſeth in that booke of his, which he entitleth <hi>De vtilitate ex adverſis capienda;</hi> and ſure his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is not to be rejected. Let the Hare then returne in vſe, and be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admitted to his former prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, ſo he be not too old, but of a competent age, as of a yeare or leſſe. But as for water-foule, you ſhall doe well to abſtaine from the ſame.</p>
               <p>Concerning fiſh, though it be for the moſt part vnwholeſome, and apt to breede <hi>excrementitious</hi> and ſlimie humors, yet for a change you may ſometimes eate ſome river-fiſh, that is firme and not ſlimie, as Trouts,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:16769:42"/>
Gudgeons, Pikes, Perches, and the like, either broyled, or boyled in Wine (if you will goe to the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) rather than in Water, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected with Fenell, Spearemints, Thyme, Roſemary, Parſley or the like. But for Mints in particular, let thoſe women, that come to the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for fruitfulneſſe, refraine the ſame, becauſe it is thought it hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth conception. At your fruit you may vſe ſome Raiſins of the Sunne, a bit of Marmelade, a roaſted War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don or Pepin mith Carrowayes, or the like; But in all this you muſt be ſparing.</p>
               <p>Now for an end of all, I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat what I haue touched before, namely, that you avoyde varietie of diſhes. For the nature of ſeverall meates being diverſe, and ſometimes cleane oppoſite and contrary one to another, &amp; ſome ſooner concocted, and other later, from hence thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills will ariſe, againſt which you
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:16769:42"/>
come to ſeeke helpe from the water, as crudities, wind-gripings, paine of the reines, obſtructions of the <hi>meſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raicall</hi> veines, rawneſſe of the <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> and conſequently of the bloud, which ſhall be made of the ſame, and ſuch like inconveniences, which by a ſober and moderate dyet may be avoyded.</p>
               <p>Thus much concerning meate. As for drinke, good ordinary cleare Beere, and of an indifferent ſtrength and age, is beſt, and it is the ordinary drinke of this Iſland, and which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth beſt with the nature of thoſe which are bred in it. Yet if any ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving beene vſed to drinke Wine at meales, deſire to continue the ſame, I am not againſt it, if ſo be they be not of too hot a conſtitution, and haue no principall part offended through exceſſe of heate; For a cup of Wine or two at meales doth but helpe to make the better digeſtion. And for that purpoſe Sacke or Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:16769:43"/>
are better than white Wine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe white Wine, by the <hi>diurecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> faculty it hath, paſſeth too ſoone away, and before the <hi>Chylus</hi> bee throughly perfected, and ſo it may carrie ſome of the Chylus rawe and vnconcocted with it, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently breede crudities and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions. And thus much concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning dyet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion of this Treatiſe.</head>
               <p>HAving briefly runne through the chiefeſt things needfull to be knowne and practiſed by ſuch, as ſhall deſire to vſe this Water, I will here end with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation vnto them to be well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed concerning the nature of their diſeaſes before they come, and when they are come, to obſerue the rules &amp; directions contained in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, as alſo to be conſtant in the vſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:16769:43"/>
of the Water. And although per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome of them perceiue little or no benefite at firſt by the ſame, yet let them not be diſcouraged, but perſevere in the vſe of it. For ſome having beene there once with ſmall or no profit at all, the next yeare after, vpon a ſecond tryall, haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home perfectly cured. It is the ordinary reward of conſtancie and perſeverance in the end to hitte the marke they ayme at. Every thing in this world hath a certaine period, before which it cannot come to a full perfection. And ſo herewith I wiſh all happie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous ſucceſſe to all ſuch, as ſhall come to theſe Springs, and will be readie at all times to affoord them my beſt helpe and counſell.</p>
               <p>Now as for this Treatiſe, I doe not looke it ſhould haue a priviledge aboue all other writings, to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from controllement and carping; For it were better lucke,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:16769:44"/>
than any man ever had, that expoſed himſelfe to the cenſure of the world. There are farre more fooles, than wiſe men in the world, and as a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard</hi> well obſerveth, <hi>Vn loco haze ciento,</hi> one foole maketh an hundreth more ſuch (moſt men having their wittes pinned vpon another mans ſleeue) and the greater foole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly is the bolder cenſurer, which maketh Bookes to be variouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, liked, and entertained, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the varietie of the Readers vnderſtanding and capacitie.</p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Pro captu lectoris habent ſua fata libelli.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Vpon the readers wit the fates of Bookes depend.</p>
               <p>But the beſt is, that I ever was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſſe of the multitude, as well in this, as in all things elſe. If the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Reader finde any juſt fault with any thing contained in this
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:16769:44"/>
Treatiſe, let him remember that <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum eſt errare,</hi> that to erre is inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the frailtie of our humane nature. But I never was ſo wedded to mine owne opinions and concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but that vpon better informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I ever was, and ever will be willing to acknowledge mine er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, if I committed, or ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any, without eſteeming it any ſhame ſo to doe, no more than many good and worthy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors haue done, when they publiſhed their retractations.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
